Register of the Poland. Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji Records, 1939-1945
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji Records,
1939-1945
59008
Poland. Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji
246 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 8 envelopes, 13 microfilm reels (105 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, bulletins, memoirs, and photographs, relating to conditions in Poland during World War II, deportation of Poles to the Soviet Union, the Katyn Forest Massacre, and activities of Polish armed forces and of the Polish Government-in-Exile. Includes release certificates and reports of several thousand Polish deportees released from the Soviet Union in 1941. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/41/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (279 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/41/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Access Points
Poland. Polskie Sily Zbrojne. Armia Polska w ZSSR; Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Deportations from Poland; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile; World War, 1939-1945--Poland; Poland; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945
Introduction
The origins of the Ministry of Information and Documentation go back to the inception of the Polish government in exile in October 1939 in Paris. At first it had neither a definite organizational structure nor a name. It was referred to as the Office (urzad) or Bureau of Information and Documentation. By April 1940, the unit was named Center of Information and Documentation, and in September 1940 the Center was reorganized into the Ministry of Information and Documentation, a designation it carried for the remainder of the war and in the years that followed.
During the early months of its existence the office, comprised of information and documentation sections, was headed by Deputy Prime Minister Stanislaw Stronski, who was directly in charge of its documentation section. The information section was headed by Minister Marian Seyda. Stanislaw Stronski was in charge of the Ministry of Information and Documentation until March 1943, when his position was taken over by Stanislaw Kot, who headed the Ministry in the cabinet of Stanislaw Mikolajczyk, until the resignation of that government in November 1944. Kot's successor was Adam Pragier, who was Minister of Information and Documentation until 1949.
The Ministry of Information and Documentation was the main information and propaganda unit of the Polish government in exile. It coordinated and facilitated the dissemination of information in support of the Polish war effort through its publishing and radio programs. The Ministry also documented and analyzed the conditions and developments in occupied Poland. One of its units, for example, the Research Section headed by Wiktor Sukiennicki, was assigned the task of systematically reviewing and summarizing the testimonies of former Polish prisoners and deportees to Soviet Russia, with a view to document the entry of the Red Army into Poland, the first weeks of Soviet occupation, the October 1939 "elections", and the consequent sovietization of the occupied territories. Thousands of original Soviet camp release certificates, statements of survivors, and detailed summaries of Soviet occupation compiled by the Research Section for every county of Eastern Poland, make up about forty percent of the volume of the Ministry's collection.
Most of the archives of the Ministry of Information and Documentation, together with those of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, were moved from London to Dublin at the end of the war, and remained in storage for more than a decade. In 1959, in keeping with the agreement reached between the Hoover Institution and Aleksander Zawisza, Minister of Foreign Affairs in the Polish government in exile, the archives were shipped to their new home at Stanford.
The collection of the Ministry of Information and Documentation in the Hoover Institution Archives occupies about 31 linear meters. A smaller portion of the Ministry's archives, 3.6 linear meters, is preserved in the Polish Institute and Sikorski Museum in London. Two Hoover collections in large measure complement the archives of the Ministry of Information. One of these is the Wladyslaw Anders Collection, consisting mostly of over 18,000 statements and reports of former Polish prisoners and deportees to Soviet Russia. The other collection is that of the Polish Government Information Center (Polskie Rzadowe Centrum Informacyjne), the New York agency of the Ministry of Information and Documentation.
Preliminary processing of the collection was provided in the 1980s by the late Helena Sworakowska. Detailed processing and preservation microfilming were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities in 1997 and by matching funds from the Taube Family Foundation.
In addition, the grant provides depositing a microfilm copy of these materials in the State Archives of Poland in Warsaw
Maciej Siekierski
November 1998
Series Description
- OFFICE FILE, 1939-1945., Boxes 1-23
  Correspondence, bulletins, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and other material relating to the operations of the Polish Ministry of Information and Documentation. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- POLISH GOVERNMENT-IN-EXILE, 1939-1944., Boxes 23-34
  Addresses, corres- pondence, decrees, notes, speeches, printed matter, and other material relating to the operations of the Polish Government-in-Exile in London. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- POLISH DIPLOMATIC OUTPOSTS, 1939-1945., Boxes 35-60
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, press reviews, clippings, printed matter, and other material relating to operations of various consulates, embassies and legations. Arranged alphabetically by country and therein by organization
- POLISH ARMED FORCES, 1940-1944., Boxes 60-66
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, printed matter and other material relating to various branches of the Polish military forces. Arranged alphabetically by military division and therein by subject
- POLISH PRESS AGENCY (PARIS), 1939-1943., Boxes 66-71
  Bulletins, cor- respondence, reports, press reviews, radio broadcasts, printed matter, and other material relating to operations of the Polish Press Agency in Paris. Arranged by branch and therein by physical form
- POLISH RESEARCH CENTER (JERUSALEM), 1943-1944., Box 71
  Correspondence, memoranda, and notes relating to operations of the Polish Research Center in Jerusalem. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- POLISH INFORMATION CENTER (NEW YORK), 1940-1944., Boxes 71-79
  Bulletins, correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter relating to operations of the Polish Information Center in New York. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- POLAND, 1938-1945., Boxes 79-109
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, clippings, printed matter, and other material relating to events and conditions in Poland. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- POLES DEPORTED TO THE SOVIET UNION, 1939-1945., Boxes 110-124
  Diaries, identity records, memoirs, and reports of Poles deported to the Soviet Union. Arranged alphabetically by subject and therein by physical form
- POLES ABROAD, 1939-1943., Boxes 124-130
  Bulletins, correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, printed matter, and other material relating to activities of Poles in foreign countries. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1945., Boxes 130-149
  Bulletins, correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, printed matter, and other material. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- MICROFILMS, 1942-1943., Box 150
  11 microfilm reels of unidentified documents
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1939-1945., Box 151 and Photo file
  599 prints depicting Polish military personnel, military operations, scenes in Warsaw, Poland, German atrocities, destruction and concentration camps, Polish statesmen and dignitaries, and various places of interest in Poland during World War II
- RELEASE CERTIFICATES ("UDOSTOVERENIA"), 1941 August-September., Boxes 152-184
  Nearly 13,500 certificates issued by the NKVD after the Polish-Soviet agreement of July 1941, releasing Polish deportees from forced labor camps and other places of detention. Arranged alphabetically by name of deportee. Each name has also been entered on-line in a separate database, along with indication of father's name, camp name, date and place of birth, names of other family members, and box number. The names use standard Polish spelling and diacritical marks; because of that, the computer has alphabetized the names in a sequence that is not quite the correct alphabetical one. Please consult reference archivist for searches in that database. Hard copies of both databases are in separate binders.
- REPORTS OF POLISH DEPORTEES, 1941., Boxes 185-247
  Nearly 12,000 questionnaires ("ankiety"), statements, and depositions of Polish deportees (as well as of some Polish prisoners of war in Box 246) collected by the Bureau of Documents of the Polish Armed Forces (Referat Historyczny Polskich Sil Zbrojnych) after evacuation to the Middle East. Arranged by name of province, and therein alphabetically by name of county. This series also includes related studies as well as copies and excerpts of some of the reports, which are filed after the orginal ones. Each name of deportee for whom we have an original report has also been entered on-line in a separate database, along with indication of profession, province, county or city, and box number (more biographical information is found in the report itself). The names use standard Polish spelling and diacritical marks; because of that, the computer has alphabetized the names in a sequence that is not quite the correct alphabetical one. Please consult reference archivist for searches in that database. Hard copies of both databases are in separate binders.
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1939-1945
  - General
    - Bulletins
      - General
        - General, 1940 (Box 1., Folder 1-2)
        - Daily bulletins relating to conditions in Poland, 1940
          - February
            - 6-14 (Folder 3)
            - 15-22 (Folder 4)
            - 23-28 (Folder 5)
          - April-May (Folder 6)
          - June 1-13 (Box 2., Folder 1)
      - La decade polonaise, 1940
        - January-February (Folder 2)
        - March-May (Folder 3)
      - Komunikat Radiowy
        - 1944
          - January-May (Folder 4)
          - June-August (Folder 5)
          - [unittitle added: see error report]
          - September-October (Box 3., Folder 1)
          - November-December (Folder 2)
        - 1945 January-February (Folder 3)
      - Servico Polonez de Informacoes
        - 1940 (Folder 4)
        - 1941 (Box 4., Folder 1)
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - 1939-1940 (Folder 3)
        - 1940
          - July-August (Folder 4)
          - September (Folder 5)
          - October (Folder 6)
          - November (Box 5., Folder 1)
          - December (Folder 2-3)
        - 1941
          - January-February (Folder 4)
          - February (Folder 5)
          - March (Folder 6)
          - April-May (Folder 7)
          - May-June (Box 6., Folder 1)
          - July (Folder 2)
          - August (Folder 3)
          - August-September> (Folder 4)
          - September (Folder 5)
          - October (Folder 6)
        - October-November (Box 7., Folder 1)
          - November-December (Folder 2)
          - December (Folder 3)
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 4)
        - 1943 (Folder 5)
        - 1943 (Box 8., Folder 1)
      - Film Section
        - 1939-1941 (Folder 2)
        - 1942 (Folder 3)
        - 1943
          - January-February (Folder 4)
          - March (Folder 5)
          - April-May (Box 9., Folder 1)
          - June-July (Folder 2)
          - August-October (Folder 3)
          - November-December (Folder 4)
      - Lisbon Office
        - 1940 October-December (Folder 5)
        - 1941
          - January (Box 10, Folder 1)
          - February-March (Folder 2)
          - April-May (Folder 3)
          - June-December (Folder 4)
        - 1942 (Folder 5)
        - 1943
          - January-April (Folder 6)
          - May-June (Box 11., Folder 1)
          - July-September (Folder 2)
          - October-November (Folder 3)
          - December (Folder 4)
        - 1944 (Folder 5)
      - Ministry of Finance (Ministerstwo Skarbu)
        - 1941
          - January-February (Folder 6)
          - March-April (Folder 7)
          - May-June (Box 12., Folder 1)
          - July (Folder 2)
          - August-September (Folder 3)
          - October (Folder 4)
          - November (Folder 5)
          - December (Folder 6)
      - Photography Section
        - General, 1943
          - January-March (Box 13., Folder 1)
          - April-June (Folder 2)
          - July-September (Folder 3)
        - Borman, Antoni
          - 1941 (Folder 4)
          - 1942 (Folder 5)
          - 1943 (Folder 6)
      - Radio Section (Radio Polskie)
        - 1942
          - January-April (Folder 7)
          - May-December (Folder 8)
        - 1943
          - January-February (Box 14., Folder 1)
          - March-May (Folder 2)
          - June-August (Folder 3)
          - September-November (Folder 4)
          - December (Folder 5)
        - 1944 (Folder 6)
      - Scotland Office
        - Edinburgh
          - 1941 (Box 15., Folder 1)
          - 1942
            - January-March (Folder 2)
            - April-May (Folder 3)
            - June-July (Folder 4)
            - August-September (Folder 5)
            - October-November (Folder 6)
            - December (Folder 7)
          - 1943
            - January-February (Folder 8)
            - March-April (Box 16., Folder 1)
            - May-July (Folder 2)
            - August-December (Folder 3)
        - Glasgow, 1944 March-December (Folder 4)
    - Propaganda file, 1943 (Folder 5)
    - Reorganization file, 1943 (Folder 6)
    - Reorganization file, 1943 (Box 17., Folder 1)
    - Reports
      - General
        - 1939 (Folder 2)
        - 1944
          - January-February (Folder 3)
          - March-April (Folder 4)
          - May-June (Folder 5)
          - July-December (Box 18., Folder 1)
      - German radio broadcasts, 1940
        - June-September (Folder 2)
        - October (Folder 3)
        - November (Folder 4)
  - British Section. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, 1943 (Folder 5)
  - Library. Lists
    - Books purchased
      - 1943-1944 (Folder 6)
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 7)
    - Holdings, 1943 (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - Press Section
    - Bulletin. Przeglad Spraw Polskich w Prasie Wielkiej Brytanji, 1941-1942 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Censorship of Polish publications, 1942-1943 (Folder 3)
      - Merger of Dziennik Polski and Dziennik Zolnierza, 1943 (Folder 4)
      - Poland in British and Allied press, 1943
        - January-May (Folder 5)
        - June-September (Folder 6)
        - October-December (Folder 7)
      - Poland in the International News Service (Hearst Press), 1941 May-July (Folder 8)
      - Polish emigre press, 1939 November-1940 April (Box 20., Folder 1)
      - Polish press in Great Britain
        - General
          - 1941
            - January (Folder 2)
            - February (Folder 3)
            - March (Folder 4)
            - April-May (Folder 5)
            - June (Box 21., Folder 1)
            - July (Folder 2)
            - August (Folder 3)
            - Septebmer-October (Folder 4)
            - November-December (Folder 5)
          - 1942 (Folder 6)
          - 1942 (Box 22., Folder 1-2)
          - 1943 (Folder 3)
        - London, 1940
          - August-September (Folder 4)
          - October-December (Folder 5)
      - Union of Polish Journalists in Great Britain, 1943 (Folder 6)
    - Instructions for journalists, 1940 February-March (Folder 7)
- POLISH GOVERNMENT-IN-EXILE, 1939-1944
  - General
    - Addresses to the people in occupied Poland by President Wladyslaw Raczkiewicz and General Sikorski, 1939 September-November (Box 23., Folder 1)
    - Clippings
      - London press relating to the Polish Government-in-exile
        - 1940-1941 (Folder 2)
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 3)
      - Raczkiewicz, Wladyslaw
        - 1940-1941 (Folder 4)
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 5)
    - Personal files
      - Kot, Stanislaw (Minister of Information and Documentation, 1943-1944)
        - Correspondence
          - General
            - 1943
              - March (Folder 6)
              - April (Folder 7)
              - May-June (Folder 8)
              - July-September (Box 24., Folder 1)
              - October (Folder 2)
              - November-December (Folder 3)
            - 1944
              - January-February (Folder 4)
              - March-June (Folder 5)
              - July-September (Folder 6)
              - October-December (Box 25., Folder 1)
          - Council of Ministers (Rada Ministrow)
            - 1943
              - March-June (Folder 2)
              - July-October (Folder 3)
              - November (Folder 4)
              - December (Folder 5)
            - 1944 (Folder 6)
          - Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych), 1943 (Box 26., Folder 1)
          - Ministry of the Interior (Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych), 1943-1944 (Folder 2)
          - Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare (Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej), 1943 (Folder 3)
          - Ministry of National Defence (Ministerstwo Obrony Narodowej), 1943
            - January-September (Folder 4)
            - October-December (Folder 5)
          - Ministry of Reconstruction of Public Administration (Ministerstwo Odbudowy Administracji Publicznej)in Postwar Poland, 1943 (Folder 6)
          - Polish Board of Education, 1943 (Folder 7)
        - Speeches, 1943 (Box 27., Folder 1)
      - Stronski, Stanislaw (Minister of Information and Documentation, 1940-1942)
        - Correspondence
          - 1940
            - January-April (Folder 2)
            - May-July (Folder 3)
            - August (Folder 4-5)
            - September (Box 28., Folder 1-3)
            - October (Folder 4-5)
            - November (Box 29., Folder 1-2)
            - December (Folder 3)
          - 1941
            - January (Folder 4)
            - February (Folder 5)
            - March (Box 30., Folder 1)
            - April (Folder 2)
            - May (Folder 3)
            - June (Folder 4)
            - July (Folder 5-6)
            - August (Box 31., Folder 1)
            - September (Folder 2)
            - October (Folder 3)
            - November-December (Folder 4)
          - 1942
            - February-August (Folder 5)
            - September-October (Folder 6)
            - November-December (Folder 7)
          - 1943
            - January-February (Box 32, Folder 1)
            - March (Folder 2)
        - Dispatches to Polish diplomatic outposts, 1941 (Folder 3)
        - Speeches, 1939-1943 (Folder 4)
  - Council of Ministers (Rada Ministrow)
    - Correspondence, decrees, notes
      - 1939
        - November (Folder 5)
        - December (Folder 6)
      - 1940
        - January-April (Folder 7)
        - May-December (Box 33., Folder 1)
      - 1941
        - March-August (Folder 2)
        - September-December (Folder 3)
      - 1942 (Folder 4)
    - Financial records, 1942 (Folder 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych). Confidential bulletins, 1943-1944 (Box 34., Folder 1)
  - National Council (Rada Narodowa)
    - Clippings from Polish emigre press
      - 1942 (Folder 2)
      - 1943 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1940-1941 (Folder 4)
      - 1942 (Folder 5)
      - 1943 (Folder 6)
    - Financial records, 1944 (Folder 7)
- POLISH DIPLOMATIC OUTPOSTS, 1939-1945
  - Africa
    - General. Correspondence of Polish Consulates in Brazzaville, Casablanca, Dakar, Dar es Salaam, Nairobi, 1943-1944 (Box 35., Folder 1)
    - South Africa
      - Poland. Agencja Konsularna (Johannesburg). Correspondence and clippings, 1940, 1942 (Folder 2)
      - Poland. Konsulat (Capetown). Correspon- (Folder 3)
      - dence, 1940, 1942
      - Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Pretoria). Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Folder 4)
  - Algeria - Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Algiers). Correspondence, l943-1944 (Folder 5)
  - Argentina - Poland. Poselstwo (Argentina). Correspondence
    - 1940 (Folder 6)
    - 1941
      - January-June (Folder 7)
      - July-December (Box 36., Folder 1)
    - 1942 (Folder 2)
    - 1943
      - January-June (Folder 3)
      - July-December (Folder 4)
    - 1944 (Folder 5)
  - Australia - Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Sydney). Correspondence, 1943 (Folder 6-7)
  - Belgium - Poland. Poselstwo (Belgium). Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Folder 8)
  - Brazil
    - Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Curitiba). Correspondence
      - 1940 (Folder 9)
      - 1941 (Box 37., Folder 1)
      - 1942-1943 (Folder 2)
    - Poland. Poselstwo (Brazil)
      - Correspondence
        - 1940 (Folder 3)
        - 1941 (Folder 4)
        - 1942 (Folder 5)
        - 1943
          - January-June (Folder 6)
          - July-September (Folder 7)
          - October-December (Folder 8)
      - Decoded telegrams, 1944 (Folder 9)
  - Canada
    - Poland. Konsulat (Montreal). Correspondence
      - 1940-1942 (Folder 10)
      - 1943 (Box 38., Folder 1)
    - Poland. Konsulat (Winnipeg). Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Folder 2)
    - Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Ottawa)
      - Clippings relating to conditions in Poland, 1940 (Folder 3)
      - Correspondence
        - 1940
          - April-August (Folder 4)
          - September-December (Folder 5)
        - 1941
          - January-April (Folder 6)
          - May-June (Folder 7)
          - July (Folder 8)
          - August-November (Folder 9)
    - Poland. Poselstwo (Canada). Correspondence
      - 1942 (Box 39., Folder 1)
      - 1943
        - January-March (Folder 2)
        - April-June (Folder 3)
        - July-August (Folder 4)
        - September-October (Folder 5)
        - November-December (Folder 6)
      - 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Catholic Church. Poland. Ambasada (Catholic Church). Correspondence
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 8)
    - 1941 (Folder 9)
    - 1942 (Box 40., Folder 1)
    - 1943-1944 (Folder 2)
  - Chile - Poland. Poselstwo (Chile). Correspondence
    - 1940 (Folder 3)
    - 1941 (Folder 4)
    - 1942-1944 (Folder 5)
  - China
    - Poland. Ambasada (China). Correspondence
      - 1942 (Folder 6)
      - 1943
        - January-February (Folder 7)
        - March-April (Folder 8)
        - May-June (Folder 9)
        - July-August (Box 41., Folder 1)
        - September-October (Folder 2)
        - November-December (Folder 3)
      - 1944
        - January-March (Folder 4)
        - April-December (Folder 5)
    - Poland. Poselstwo (China)
      - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Folder 6)
      - Decoded telegrams, 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Colombia - Poland. Poselstwo (Colombia). Correspondence
    - 1943 (Folder 8)
    - 1943-1944 (Folder 9)
  - Cuba - Poland. Poselstwo (Cuba). Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 42., Folder 1)
  - Egypt - Poland. Poselstwo (Egypt)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Folder 2)
    - Telegrams
      - 1941-1943 (Folder 3)
      - 1944 (Folder 4)
  - France - Poland. Ambasada (France). Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Folder 5)
  - Hungary - Poland. Poselstwo (Hungary)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Folder 6)
    - Decoded telegrams, 1939 August-September (Folder 7)